<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY appversion10 "1.0">
  <!ENTITY appversion11 "1.1">
  <!ENTITY appversion12 "1.2">
  <!ENTITY appversion13 "1.3">
  <!ENTITY date10 "May 2008">
  <!ENTITY date11 "Październik 2008">
  <!ENTITY date12 "Czerwiec 2009">
  <!ENTITY date13 "March 2010">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "1.3">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Device Driver Utility</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Zarządzanie sterownikami urządzeń">
]>
<!-- 
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
  
-->
<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="ang">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->

<title>&appname; - Instrukcja obsługi</title>
<articleinfo> 

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2008, 2010</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

 -->
<!-- If a role is not specified, the publisher/author is the same for
     all versions of the document.
 -->
<releaseinfo>Oracle Solaris 11 Express</releaseinfo> <pubdate>November 2010</pubdate>
<publisher> 
<publishername>Oracle Corporation</publishername> 
<address>
<street>500 Oracle Parkway</street>
<city>Redwood City</city><state>CA</state><postcode>94065</postcode>
<country>U.S.A.</country>
</address></publisher> 
<copyright>
<year>2008, 2010</year> 
<holder>Oracle Corporation</holder> 
</copyright> 

<!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and 
     other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
     any of this.

    <revhistory>
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion13;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date13;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion12;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date12;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion11;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date11;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion10;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date10;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    </revhistory> 
 -->

<abstract role="description">
<para>Podręcznik użytkownika dla <application>Zarządzania sterownikami urządzeń</application></para>
</abstract>
<legalnotice><para>This software and related documentation are provided under a
license agreement containing restrictions on use and disclosure and are
protected by intellectual property laws. Except as expressly permitted in your
license agreement or allowed by law, you may not use, copy, reproduce,
translate, broadcast, modify, license, transmit, distribute, exhibit, perform,
publish, or display any part, in any form, or by any means. Reverse
engineering, disassembly, or decompilation of this software, unless required by
law for interoperability, is prohibited.</para>
<para>The information contained herein is subject to change without notice and
is not warranted to be error-free. If you find any errors, please report them
to us in writing.</para>
<para>If this is software or related software documentation that is delivered
to the U.S. Government or anyone licensing it on behalf of the U.S. Government,
the following notice is applicable:</para>
<para>U.S. GOVERNMENT RIGHTS Programs, software, databases, and related
documentation and technical data delivered to U.S. Government customers are
“commercial computer software” or “commercial technical
data” pursuant to the applicable Federal Acquisition Regulation and
agency-specific supplemental regulations. As such, the use, duplication,
disclosure, modification, and adaptation shall be subject to the restrictions
and license terms set forth in the applicable Government contract, and, to the
extent applicable by the terms of the Government contract, the additional
rights set forth in FAR 52.227-19, Commercial Computer Software License
(December 2007). Oracle America, Inc., 500 Oracle Parkway, Redwood City, CA
94065.</para>
<para>This software or hardware is developed for general use in a variety of
information management applications. It is not developed or intended for use in
any inherently dangerous applications, including applications which may create
a risk of personal injury. If you use this software or hardware in dangerous
applications, then you shall be responsible to take all appropriate fail-safe,
backup, redundancy, and other measures to ensure its safe use. Oracle
Corporation and its affiliates disclaim any liability for any damages caused by
use of this software or hardware in dangerous applications.</para>
<para>Oracle and Java are registered trademarks of Oracle and/or its
affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective owners.</para>
<para>AMD, Opteron, the AMD logo, and the AMD Opteron logo are trademarks or
registered trademarks of Advanced Micro Devices. Intel and Intel Xeon are
trademarks or registered trademarks of Intel Corporation. All SPARC trademarks
are used under license and are trademarks or registered trademarks of SPARC
International, Inc. UNIX is a registered trademark licensed through X/Open
Company, Ltd.</para>
<para>This software or hardware and documentation may provide access to or
information on content, products, and services from third parties. Oracle
Corporation and its affiliates are not responsible for and expressly disclaim
all warranties of any kind with respect to third-party content, products, and
services. Oracle Corporation and its affiliates will not be responsible for any
loss, costs, or damages incurred due to your access to or use of third-party
content, products, or services.</para>
</legalnotice>
</articleinfo> 

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->


<!-- ============= Overview ============================== -->
<sect1 id="ddu-introduction">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Overview</title>
    <para>Device Driver Utility is an application that provides information about those devices of your native system that have the Oracle Solaris Operating System (OS) installed. Zarządzanie sterownikami urządzeń pozwala połączyć się z Systemem pakowania obrazów (IPS) i wyszukać sterowników dla urządzeń, które nie mają ich przypisanych. IPS jest repozytorium paczek systemu operacyjnego Oracle Solaris. Możesz znaleźć odpowiednie sterowniki do urządzeń w tym repozytorium. Użyj aplikacji Zarządzanie sterownikami urządzeń do wykonania następujących operacji:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Zdobądź informacje o urządzeniach zainstalowanych w twoim natywnym systemie i sprawdź, czy istnieją odpowiednie dla nich sterowniki.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Search drivers for your system devices that do not have corresponding driver attached.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Download and install the device drivers for devices on your system.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Wyślij konfigurację systemu do HCL.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<para>Device Driver Utility is integrated with the Oracle Solaris OS. This utility requires at least Python version 2.4 and Perl version 5.8. However, the Oracle Solaris OS is by default integrated with Perl version 5.8 and Python version 2.4.</para>

</sect1>

<!--============== DDU interface ===========-->
<sect1 id="ddu-interface">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Interface</title>
   <para>Device Driver Utility starts running on your system automatically when you start the system. If the Device Driver Utility application finds any missing driver, it is notified on your desktop. The missing driver is installed automatically from the repository.
    </para>
    <para>To invoke Device Driver Utility manually, click Applications->System->Device Driver Utility on the Oracle Solaris OS desktop. The Device Driver Utility window is displayed as shown in the following figure. 
    </para>
 <figure id="DDU_Main_Window">
  <title>Główne okno Zarządzania sterownikami urządzeń</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-main.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Główne okno Zarządzania sterownikami urządzeń</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>
 <para>
Kolumna Rodzaje pokazuje nazwy kategorii urządzeń. Różne kategorie urządzeń to Audio, CPU, Pamięć, Sieć, Przechowywanie, USB, Video i Inne. Jeśli używasz laptopa, pojawi się kategoria Bateria pokazująca informacje o stanie baterii laptopa. Kolumna Urządzenia pokazuje listę kontrolerów i nazw urządzeń odpowiadającą każdej kategorii urządzenia. Kolumna Sterowniki pokazuje nazwy obecnych sterowników urządzeń lub stan sterownika każdego urządzenia. The name of the device driver is displayed if the driver exists for the respective device in the system. Otherwise, the status of the driver is displayed.
 </para>
    <para>Sterownik urządzenia może być w jednym z następujących stanów:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>IPS: Indicates that there is no driver in the system but the driver exists in the IPS. The Info link provides the information about the package that exists for the corresponding device in the IPS repository. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>SVR4: Indicates that there is no driver in the system but a SVR4 (System V Revision 4) package exists. The Info link provides the corresponding SVR4 package information.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>DU: Indicates that there is no driver in the system but a DU package exists. The Info link provides the relative DU package information. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>UNK: Indicates that the status of the driver is unknown and probably there is no driver for the corresponding device.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Note: When you click the Info link, the text field in the Package radio button is populated with the relative package information. Click the Install button to install the package.</para>
    <para>Okno Zarządzanie sterownikami urządzeń zawiera następujące przyciski:</para> 
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Odśwież: każe systemowi szukać urządzeń Jeśli status sterownika to Brak sterownika, kliknij przycisk Odśwież. To przeszukuje system pod kątem urządzeń oraz odpowiadającym im sterowników i wyświetla informacje. Ta akcja może zmienić poprzedni status sterownika urządzenia. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Package: Installs driver from the IPS repository. Type the package name in the text field and click the Install button to install the relative package.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>File/URL: Installs driver from the URL or the native system. Type the file name or URL of the package in the text box. Click the Browse button to locate the package on your system and install the package. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Pomoc: Wyświetl pomoc online dla Zarządzania sterownikami urządzeń. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Zamknij: zamyka Zarządzanie sterownikami urządzeń.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Wyślij: Wysyła konfigurację twojego systemu do Listy Kompatybilnych Urządzeń (HCL). </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Install: Installs the missing drivers. The Install pop-up window is displayed indicating the progress of installation.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<!--============== Working with DDU  ===========-->
<sect1 id="ddu-working">
  <title>Working with Device Driver Utility</title>
    <para>Aby uzyskać informacje na temat sprzętu twojego systemu:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Kliknij prawym przyciskiem myszki na dowolne urządzenie i kliknij Szczegółowe informacje. W okienku pop-up, które się wyświetla, możesz przeczytać szczegółowe informacje o zainstalowanym sprzęcie.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<figure id="DDU_Detail_Window">
  <title>Okno Informacyjne Zarządzania sterownikami urządzeń</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-detail.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Okno Informacyjne Zarządzania sterownikami urządzeń</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

    <para>To install drivers:</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to install the driver from the repository:</para>


    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click on the device name for which you want to install the driver.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Info link next to the driver status.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the Package radio button. If the Device Driver Utility has the repository and the package information in it's database, the package details will automatically populate the text field in the Package radio button.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the relevant repository and type the package details manually, if the text field is not filled up automatically.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Kliknij przycisk Install (Instaluj).</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <para>If you have downloaded a driver package to your native system, perform the following steps to install the driver:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click on the device name for which you want to install the driver.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the File/URL radio button.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Browse. The Browse Driver Packages window is displayed as shown in the following figure:</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<figure id="DDU_Browse_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility File Browser Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-browse.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility File Browse Window</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Select the package file.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Kliknij przycisk Install (Instaluj). Okno Instalacja sterowników wyświetla postęp instalacji.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
  <figure id="DDU_Install_Window">
  <title>Okno Instalacji sterowników Narzędzia zarządzania sterownikami</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-install.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Okno Instalacji sterowników Narzędzia zarządzania sterownikami</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>
 

    <para>To add another repository on the system</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to add a new repository to your system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click the drop-down list that is next to the Package radio button.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select Add repository. The Repositories manager window is displayed as shown in the following figure:</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
  <figure id="DDU_repo_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Add RepoWindow</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-addrepo.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility Add RepoWindow</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>Type the name and URL of the repository.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Add.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Aby wysłać zgłoszenie o twoim systemie do HCL:</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to submit your system to HCL.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click the Submit button on the main window of Device Driver Utility. The Submit Information To HCL window is displayed as shown in the following figure. </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<figure id="DDU_Submit_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Submission Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-submit.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility Submission Window</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

<para>Type the following system information in the corresponding text fields: </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Rodzaj systemu: Wybierz rodzaj systemu z listy. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Nazwa producenta: Wpisz nazwę producenta systemu, np. Hewlett-Packard lub Dell.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Model: Wpisz model testowanego systemu, np. HP xw8400 Workstation </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Producent BIOS/Firmware: wpisz informację z ekranu konfiguracji BIOS, który zwykle jest wyświetlany podczas ładowania systemu.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Rodzaj CPU: Wpisz nazwę producenta CPU. Na przykład: Intel(R)Xeon(R)CPU5130@2.00GHz. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Informacje zebrane: Upewnij się, czy te informacje są zgodne ze szczegółami, które podałeś i wyślij do firmy Oracle.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Uwagi ogólne: Wpisz jakąkolwiek dodatkową informacje o systemie, którego szczegóły są wysłane. Możesz podać informację, czy pomyślnie uruchomiłeś system i składniki do pracy z Oracle Solaris OS. </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<para>Po wysłaniu informacji, zostanie Ci wysłane potwierdzenie otrzymania wraz z łączem do miejsca, gdzie Twoja informacja jest dostępna. Zespół kontrolujący firmy Oracle sprawdzi i opublikuje informacje na temat twojego systemu w HCL.</para>
</sect1>
</article>
