<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY appversion10 "1.0">
  <!ENTITY appversion11 "1.1">
  <!ENTITY appversion12 "1.2">
  <!ENTITY appversion13 "1.3">
  <!ENTITY date10 "Μάιος 2008">
  <!ENTITY date11 "Οκτώβριος 2008">
  <!ENTITY date12 "Ιούνιος 2009">
  <!ENTITY date13 "Μάρτιος 2010">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "1.3">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών">
]>
<!-- 
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
  
-->
<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="el">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->

<title>&appname; Εγχειρίδιο χρήσης</title>
<articleinfo> 

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2008, 2010</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

 -->
<!-- If a role is not specified, the publisher/author is the same for
     all versions of the document.
 -->
<releaseinfo>Oracle Solaris 11 Express</releaseinfo> <pubdate>November 2010</pubdate>
<publisher> 
<publishername>Oracle Corporation</publishername> 
<address>
<street>500 Oracle Parkway</street>
<city>Redwood City</city><state>CA</state><postcode>94065</postcode>
<country>U.S.A.</country>
</address></publisher> 
<copyright>
<year>2008, 2010</year> 
<holder>Oracle Corporation</holder> 
</copyright> 

<!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and 
     other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
     any of this.

    <revhistory>
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion13;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date13;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion12;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date12;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion11;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date11;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion10;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date10;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    </revhistory> 
 -->

<abstract role="description">
<para>User manual for <application>Device Driver Utility</application>.</para>
</abstract>
<legalnotice><para>This software and related documentation are provided under a
license agreement containing restrictions on use and disclosure and are
protected by intellectual property laws. Except as expressly permitted in your
license agreement or allowed by law, you may not use, copy, reproduce,
translate, broadcast, modify, license, transmit, distribute, exhibit, perform,
publish, or display any part, in any form, or by any means. Reverse
engineering, disassembly, or decompilation of this software, unless required by
law for interoperability, is prohibited.</para>
<para>The information contained herein is subject to change without notice and
is not warranted to be error-free. If you find any errors, please report them
to us in writing.</para>
<para>If this is software or related software documentation that is delivered
to the U.S. Government or anyone licensing it on behalf of the U.S. Government,
the following notice is applicable:</para>
<para>U.S. GOVERNMENT RIGHTS Programs, software, databases, and related
documentation and technical data delivered to U.S. Government customers are
“commercial computer software” or “commercial technical
data” pursuant to the applicable Federal Acquisition Regulation and
agency-specific supplemental regulations. As such, the use, duplication,
disclosure, modification, and adaptation shall be subject to the restrictions
and license terms set forth in the applicable Government contract, and, to the
extent applicable by the terms of the Government contract, the additional
rights set forth in FAR 52.227-19, Commercial Computer Software License
(December 2007). Oracle America, Inc., 500 Oracle Parkway, Redwood City, CA
94065.</para>
<para>This software or hardware is developed for general use in a variety of
information management applications. It is not developed or intended for use in
any inherently dangerous applications, including applications which may create
a risk of personal injury. If you use this software or hardware in dangerous
applications, then you shall be responsible to take all appropriate fail-safe,
backup, redundancy, and other measures to ensure its safe use. Oracle
Corporation and its affiliates disclaim any liability for any damages caused by
use of this software or hardware in dangerous applications.</para>
<para>Oracle and Java are registered trademarks of Oracle and/or its
affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective owners.</para>
<para>AMD, Opteron, the AMD logo, and the AMD Opteron logo are trademarks or
registered trademarks of Advanced Micro Devices. Intel and Intel Xeon are
trademarks or registered trademarks of Intel Corporation. All SPARC trademarks
are used under license and are trademarks or registered trademarks of SPARC
International, Inc. UNIX is a registered trademark licensed through X/Open
Company, Ltd.</para>
<para>This software or hardware and documentation may provide access to or
information on content, products, and services from third parties. Oracle
Corporation and its affiliates are not responsible for and expressly disclaim
all warranties of any kind with respect to third-party content, products, and
services. Oracle Corporation and its affiliates will not be responsible for any
loss, costs, or damages incurred due to your access to or use of third-party
content, products, or services.</para>
</legalnotice>
</articleinfo> 

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->


<!-- ============= Overview ============================== -->
<sect1 id="ddu-introduction">
  <title>Γενική επισκόπηση του εργαλείου οδηγών συσκευών </title>
    <para>Το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών είναι μια εφαρμογή η οποία παρέχει πληροφορίες για  εκείνες τις συσκευές του συστήματός σας για τις οποίες έχει εγκατασταθεί οδηγός του Oracle Solaris. Το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών σας επιτρέπει να συνδεθείτε με το IPS και να ψάξετε για οδηγούς συσκευών για τις συσκευές τις οποίες δεν έχει εγκατασταθεί οδηγός. Το IPS είναι μια αποθήκη πακέτων του λειτουργικού συστήματος Oracle Solaris. Μπορείτε να βρείτε κατάλληλους οδηγούς για τις συσκευές σε αυτή την αποθήκη. Χρησιμοποιήστε το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών για να επιτελέσετε τις παρακάτω λειτουργίες: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Να λάβετε πληροφορίες για τις συσκευές που περιέχει το σύστημά σας και να ελέγξετε αν ο αντίστοιχος οδηγός συσκευής υπάρχει.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Να ψάξετε για οδηγούς για τις συσκευές του συστήματός σας για τις οποίες δεν είναι ενεργοποιημένος ο αντίστοιχος οδηγός. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Να κατεβάσετε και να εγκαταστήσετε οδηγούς συσκευών για συσκευές του συστήματός σας.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Να αποστείλετε πληροφορίες για τη σύνθεση του συστήματός σας στο HCL. </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<para>Το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών είναι ενσωματωμένο στο Oracle Solaris. Το εργαλείο απαιτεί τουλάχιστον την Python έκδοση 2.4 και την Perl έκδοση 5.8. Πάντως το Oracle Solaris έχει ενσωματωμένες και την Perl έκδοση 5.8 και την Python έκδοση 2.4.</para>

</sect1>

<!--============== DDU interface ===========-->
<sect1 id="ddu-interface">
  <title>Η διεπαφή του εργαλείου οδηγών συσκευών </title>
   <para>Το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών ξεκινάει αυτόματα να τρέχει στο σύστημά σας όταν ξεκινάτε το σύστημα. Αν το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών βρει μια συσκευή για την οποία δεν έχει εγκατασταθεί οδηγός, αυτό φαίνεται στο γραφικό περιβάλλον εργασίας. Αυτός ο οδηγός συσκευής θα εγκατασταθεί αυτόματα από την αποθήκη.
    </para>
    <para>Για να ξεκινήσετε το εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών μη αυτόματα, απλά πατήστε Εφαρμογές->Σύστημα->Εργαλείο οδηγών συσκευών στο περιβάλλον εργασίας του Oracle Solaris. Το παράθυρο του εργαλείου οδηγών συσκευών φαίνεται εμφανίζεται όπως φαίνεται στην παρακάτω εικόνα. 
    </para>
 <figure id="DDU_Main_Window">
  <title>Κύριο παράθυρο του εργαλείου οδηγών συσκευών</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-main.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Κύριο παράθυρο του εργαλείου οδηγών συσκευών</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>
 <para>
Η στήλη τύποι δείχνει τα ονόματα των κατηγοριών συσκευών. Οι διάφορες κατηγορίες συσκευών είναι ήχου, ΚΜΕ, μνήμης, δικτύου, USB, κάρτας γραφικών και άλλες. Αν χρησιμοποιείται laptop, θα υπάρχει και κατηγορία για τις μπαταρίες η οποία θα δίνει πληροφορίες για την μπαταρία του laptop. Η στήλη με τις συσκευές δείχνει τον κατάλογο ελεγκτών και τα ονόματα συσκευών τα οποία αντιστοιχούν σε κάθε κατηγορία συσκευών. Η στήλη με τους οδηγούς δείχνει τα ονόματα υπαρχόντων οδηγών συσκευών ή την κατάσταση ενός υπάρχοντος οδηγού συσκευής για κάθε συσκευή. Το όνομα του οδηγού συσκευής φαίνεται αν ο οδηγός υπάρχει για την αντίστοιχη συσκευή στο σύστημα. Αλλιώτικα εμφανίζονται η κατάσταση του οδηγού.
 </para>
    <para>Η κατάσταση του οδηγού μπορεί να είναι μία από τις παρακάτω:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>IPS: Δηλώνει ότι δεν υπάρχει οδηγός στο σύστημα αλλά ο οδηγός υπάρχει στο IPS. Ο σύνδεσμος πληροφοριών παρέχει τις πληροφορίες για το πακέτο το οποίο υπάρχει για την αντίστοιχη συσκευή στο αποθήκη IPS. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>SVR4: Δηλώνει ότι δεν υπάρχει οδηγός στο σύστημα αλλά υπάρχει ένα πακέτο SVR4 (System V Revision 4. Ο σύνδεσμος πληροφοριών παρέχει τις πληροφορίες για το αντίστοιχο πακέτο SVR4.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>DU: Δηλώνει ότι δεν υπάρχει οδηγός στο σύστημα αλλά υπάρχει ένα πακέτο DU. Ο σύνδεσμος πληροφοριών παρέχει τις πληροφορίες για το αντίστοιχο πακέτο DU. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>UNK: Δηλώνει ότι η κατάσταση του οδηγού είναι άγνωστη και πολύ πιθανά δεν υπάρχει οδηγός για την αντίστοιχη συσκευή.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Σημείωση: όταν κάνετε κλικ στο σύνδεσμο πληροφοριών, το πεδίο κειμένου στο  δίπλα από το πλήκτρο για το Πακέτο γεμίζει με πληροφορίες σχετικές με το πακέτο. Κάντε κλικ στο πλήκτρο «Εγκατάσταση» για να εγκατασταθεί το πακέτο. </para>
    <para>Το παράθυρο του εργαλείου οδηγών συσκευών περιέχει υα παρακάτω πλήκτρα: </para> 
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Ανανέωση: Κατευθύνει το σύστημα στο να ψάξει για οδηγούς. Αν η κατάσταση ενός οδηγού συσκευής είναι Eλλείπων Οδηγός, κάντε κλικ στο πλήκτρο Ανανέωση. This searches the system for the devices and their corresponding drivers and displays the information. This action might change the previous status of the device driver. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Package: Installs driver from the IPS repository. Type the package name in the text field and click the Install button to install the relative package.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>File/URL: Installs driver from the URL or the native system. Type the file name or URL of the package in the text box. Click the Browse button to locate the package on your system and install the package. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Help: Displays the online help for Device Driver Utility. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Close: Closes the Device Driver Utility.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Submit: Submits the configurations of your system to the Oracle Solaris hardware compatibility list (HCL). </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Install: Installs the missing drivers. The Install pop-up window is displayed indicating the progress of installation.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<!--============== Working with DDU  ===========-->
<sect1 id="ddu-working">
  <title>Working with Device Driver Utility</title>
    <para>To get the hardware details of your system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Right click on any device and click Detail Information. The Hardware Detail Information pop-up window is displayed where you can find the details of your system's hardware.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<figure id="DDU_Detail_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Detail Information Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-detail.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility Detail Information Window</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

    <para>To install drivers:</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to install the driver from the repository:</para>


    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click on the device name for which you want to install the driver.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Info link next to the driver status.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the Package radio button. If the Device Driver Utility has the repository and the package information in it's database, the package details will automatically populate the text field in the Package radio button.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the relevant repository and type the package details manually, if the text field is not filled up automatically.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Install.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <para>If you have downloaded a driver package to your native system, perform the following steps to install the driver:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click on the device name for which you want to install the driver.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the File/URL radio button.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Browse. The Browse Driver Packages window is displayed as shown in the following figure:</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<figure id="DDU_Browse_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility File Browser Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-browse.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility File Browse Window</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Select the package file.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Install. The Install Driver pop-up window is displayed indicating the progress of installation.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
  <figure id="DDU_Install_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Install Driver Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-install.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility Install Driver Window</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>
 

    <para>To add another repository on the system</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to add a new repository to your system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click the drop-down list that is next to the Package radio button.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select Add repository. The Repositories manager window is displayed as shown in the following figure:</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
  <figure id="DDU_repo_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Add RepoWindow</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-addrepo.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility Add RepoWindow</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>Type the name and URL of the repository.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Add.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To Submit your System to HCL:</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to submit your system to HCL.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click the Submit button on the main window of Device Driver Utility. The Submit Information To HCL window is displayed as shown in the following figure. </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<figure id="DDU_Submit_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Submission Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject> <imagedata fileref="../C/figures/DDU-submit.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/> </imageobject> <textobject> <phrase>Device Driver Utility Submission Window</phrase> </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

<para>Type the following system information in the corresponding text fields: </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>System type: Select the type of the system from the drop-down list. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Manufacture name: Type the name of the system maker such as Hewlett-Packard or Dell.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Model: Type the complete model number for the system being tested, such as HP xw8400 Workstation. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>BIOS/Firmware Maker: Type the information on the BIOS Setup screen that is usually displayed while booting the system.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>CPU type: Type the name of the CPU maker. For instance, Intel(R)Xeon(R)CPU5130@2.00GHz. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Information Collected: Verify whether this information reflects the details that you have specified and submit the same to Oracle.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>General Notes: Type any additional information of the system whose details are submitted. You can also type the information of how successfully you got the system and components to work with the Oracle Solaris OS.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<para>Upon submission, you will get an acknowledgement of your submission and a link where your submission is available. The Oracle auditing team will check and publish your system information to HCL.</para>
</sect1>
</article>
