<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY appversion10 "1.0">
  <!ENTITY appversion11 "1.1">
  <!ENTITY appversion12 "1.2">
  <!ENTITY appversion13 "1.3">
  <!ENTITY date10 "May 2008">
  <!ENTITY date11 "October 2008">
  <!ENTITY date12 "June 2009">
  <!ENTITY date13 "March 2010">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "1.3">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Device Driver Utility</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Device Driver Utility">
]>
<!--
CDDL HEADER START

The contents of this file are subject to the terms of the
Common Development and Distribution License (the "License").
You may not use this file except in compliance with the License.

You can obtain a copy of the license at usr/src/OPENSOLARIS.LICENSE
or http://www.opensolaris.org/os/licensing.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions
and limitations under the License.

When distributing Covered Code, include this CDDL HEADER in each
file and include the License file at usr/src/OPENSOLARIS.LICENSE.
If applicable, add the following below this CDDL HEADER, with the
fields enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying
information: Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]

CDDL HEADER END

Copyright (c) 2008, 2010, Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

-->
<!-- 
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
  
-->
<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="en">
<!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
<!-- appropriate code -->

<title>&appname; Manual</title>
<articleinfo> 

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2008, 2010</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

 -->
<!-- If a role is not specified, the publisher/author is the same for
     all versions of the document.
 -->
<releaseinfo>Oracle Solaris 11 Express</releaseinfo>
<pubdate>November 2010</pubdate>
<publisher> 
<publishername>Oracle Corporation</publishername> 
<address>
<street>500 Oracle Parkway</street>
<city>Redwood City</city><state>CA</state><postcode>94065</postcode>
<country>U.S.A.</country>
</address></publisher> 
<copyright>
<year>2008, 2010</year> 
<holder>Oracle Corporation</holder> 
</copyright> 

<!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and 
     other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
     any of this.

    <revhistory>
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion13;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date13;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion12;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date12;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion11;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date11;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    <revision> 
		<revnumber>&appname; V&appversion10;</revnumber> 
		<date>&date10;</date> 
		<revdescription> 
	  		<para role="author">Oracle</para>
	  		<para role="publisher">Oracle</para>
		</revdescription> 
    </revision> 
    </revhistory> 
 -->

<abstract role="description">
<para>User manual for <application>Device Driver Utility</application>.</para>
</abstract>
<legalnotice><para>This software and related documentation are provided under a
license agreement containing restrictions on use and disclosure and are
protected by intellectual property laws. Except as expressly permitted in your
license agreement or allowed by law, you may not use, copy, reproduce,
translate, broadcast, modify, license, transmit, distribute, exhibit, perform,
publish, or display any part, in any form, or by any means. Reverse
engineering, disassembly, or decompilation of this software, unless required by
law for interoperability, is prohibited.</para>
<para>The information contained herein is subject to change without notice and
is not warranted to be error-free. If you find any errors, please report them
to us in writing.</para>
<para>If this is software or related software documentation that is delivered
to the U.S. Government or anyone licensing it on behalf of the U.S. Government,
the following notice is applicable:</para>
<para>U.S. GOVERNMENT RIGHTS Programs, software, databases, and related
documentation and technical data delivered to U.S. Government customers are
&ldquo;commercial computer software&rdquo; or &ldquo;commercial technical
data&rdquo; pursuant to the applicable Federal Acquisition Regulation and
agency-specific supplemental regulations. As such, the use, duplication,
disclosure, modification, and adaptation shall be subject to the restrictions
and license terms set forth in the applicable Government contract, and, to the
extent applicable by the terms of the Government contract, the additional
rights set forth in FAR 52.227-19, Commercial Computer Software License
(December 2007). Oracle America, Inc., 500 Oracle Parkway, Redwood City, CA
94065.</para>
<para>This software or hardware is developed for general use in a variety of
information management applications. It is not developed or intended for use in
any inherently dangerous applications, including applications which may create
a risk of personal injury. If you use this software or hardware in dangerous
applications, then you shall be responsible to take all appropriate fail-safe,
backup, redundancy, and other measures to ensure its safe use. Oracle
Corporation and its affiliates disclaim any liability for any damages caused by
use of this software or hardware in dangerous applications.</para>
<para>Oracle and Java are registered trademarks of Oracle and/or its
affiliates. Other names may be trademarks of their respective owners.</para>
<para>AMD, Opteron, the AMD logo, and the AMD Opteron logo are trademarks or
registered trademarks of Advanced Micro Devices. Intel and Intel Xeon are
trademarks or registered trademarks of Intel Corporation. All SPARC trademarks
are used under license and are trademarks or registered trademarks of SPARC
International, Inc. UNIX is a registered trademark licensed through X/Open
Company, Ltd.</para>
<para>This software or hardware and documentation may provide access to or
information on content, products, and services from third parties. Oracle
Corporation and its affiliates are not responsible for and expressly disclaim
all warranties of any kind with respect to third-party content, products, and
services. Oracle Corporation and its affiliates will not be responsible for any
loss, costs, or damages incurred due to your access to or use of third-party
content, products, or services.</para>
<para lang="fr"></para>
<para>Ce logiciel et la documentation qui l&rsquo;accompagne sont
prot&eacute;g&eacute;s par les lois sur la propri&eacute;t&eacute;
intellectuelle. Ils sont conc&eacute;d&eacute;s sous licence et soumis &agrave;
des restrictions d&rsquo;utilisation et de divulgation. Sauf disposition de
votre contrat de licence ou de la loi, vous ne pouvez pas copier, reproduire,
traduire, diffuser, modifier, breveter, transmettre, distribuer, exposer,
ex&eacute;cuter, publier ou afficher le logiciel, m&ecirc;me partiellement,
sous quelque forme et par quelque proc&eacute;d&eacute; que ce soit. Par
ailleurs, il est interdit de proc&eacute;der &agrave; toute ing&eacute;nierie
inverse du logiciel, de le d&eacute;sassembler ou de le d&eacute;compiler,
except&eacute; &agrave; des fins d&rsquo;interop&eacute;rabilit&eacute; avec
des logiciels tiers ou tel que prescrit par la loi.</para>
<para>Les informations fournies dans ce document sont susceptibles de
modification sans pr&eacute;avis. Par ailleurs, Oracle Corporation ne garantit
pas qu&rsquo;elles soient exemptes d&rsquo;erreurs et vous invite, le cas
&eacute;ch&eacute;ant, &agrave; lui en faire part par &eacute;crit.</para>
<para>Si ce logiciel, ou la documentation qui l&rsquo;accompagne, est
conc&eacute;d&eacute; sous licence au Gouvernement des Etats-Unis, ou &agrave;
toute entit&eacute; qui d&eacute;livre la licence de ce logiciel ou
l&rsquo;utilise pour le compte du Gouvernement des Etats-Unis, la notice
suivante s&rsquo;applique :</para>
<para>U.S. GOVERNMENT RIGHTS. Programs, software, databases, and related
documentation and technical data delivered to U.S. Government customers are
"commercial computer software" or "commercial technical data" pursuant to the
applicable Federal Acquisition Regulation and agency-specific supplemental
regulations. As such, the use, duplication, disclosure, modification, and
adaptation shall be subject to the restrictions and license terms set forth in
the applicable Government contract, and, to the extent applicable by the terms
of the Government contract, the additional rights set forth in FAR 52.227-19,
Commercial Computer Software License (December 2007). Oracle America, Inc., 500
Oracle Parkway, Redwood City, CA 94065.</para>
<para>Ce logiciel ou mat&eacute;riel a &eacute;t&eacute;
d&eacute;velopp&eacute; pour un usage g&eacute;n&eacute;ral dans le cadre
d&rsquo;applications de gestion des informations. Ce logiciel ou
mat&eacute;riel n&rsquo;est pas con&ccedil;u ni n&rsquo;est destin&eacute;
&agrave; &ecirc;tre utilis&eacute; dans des applications &agrave; risque,
notamment dans des applications pouvant causer des dommages corporels. Si vous
utilisez ce logiciel ou mat&eacute;riel dans le cadre d&rsquo;applications
dangereuses, il est de votre responsabilit&eacute; de prendre toutes les
mesures de secours, de sauvegarde, de redondance et autres mesures
n&eacute;cessaires &agrave; son utilisation dans des conditions optimales de
s&eacute;curit&eacute;. Oracle Corporation et ses affili&eacute;s
d&eacute;clinent toute responsabilit&eacute; quant aux dommages caus&eacute;s
par l&rsquo;utilisation de ce logiciel ou mat&eacute;riel pour ce type
d&rsquo;applications.</para>
<para>Oracle et Java sont des marques d&eacute;pos&eacute;es d&rsquo;Oracle
Corporation et/ou de ses affili&eacute;s.Tout autre nom mentionn&eacute; peut
correspondre &agrave; des marques appartenant &agrave; d&rsquo;autres
propri&eacute;taires qu&rsquo;Oracle.</para>
<para>AMD, Opteron, le logo AMD et le logo AMD Opteron sont des marques ou des
marques d&eacute;pos&eacute;es d&rsquo;Advanced Micro Devices. Intel et Intel
Xeon sont des marques ou des marques d&eacute;pos&eacute;es d&rsquo;Intel
Corporation. Toutes les marques SPARC sont utilis&eacute;es sous licence et
sont des marques ou des marques d&eacute;pos&eacute;es de SPARC International,
Inc. UNIX est une marque d&eacute;pos&eacute;e conc&eacute;d&eacute; sous
license par X/Open Company, Ltd.</para>
</legalnotice>
</articleinfo> 

<!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->


<!-- ============= Overview ============================== -->
<sect1 id="ddu-introduction">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Overview</title>
    <para>Device Driver Utility is an application that provides information about those devices of your native system that have the Oracle Solaris Operating System (OS) installed. Device Driver Utility enables you to connect to the Image Packaging System (IPS) and search device drivers for the devices that do not have drivers attached to them. IPS is a repository for the Oracle Solaris OS packages. You can find suitable drivers for the devices in this repository. Use the Device Driver Utility application to perform the following functions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Get information about devices installed on your native system and check whether their corresponding device drivers exist.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Search drivers for your system devices that do not have corresponding driver attached.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Download and install the device drivers for devices on your system.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Submit system configurations to HCL.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<para>Device Driver Utility is integrated with the Oracle Solaris OS. This utility requires at least Python version 2.4 and Perl version 5.8. However, the Oracle Solaris OS is by default integrated with Perl version 5.8 and Python version 2.4.</para>

</sect1>

<!--============== DDU interface ===========-->
<sect1 id="ddu-interface">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Interface</title>
   <para>Device Driver Utility starts running on your system automatically when you start the system. If the Device Driver Utility application finds any missing driver, it is notified on your desktop. The missing driver is installed automatically from the repository.
    </para>
    <para>To invoke Device Driver Utility manually, click Applications->System->Device Driver Utility on the Oracle Solaris OS desktop. The Device Driver Utility window is displayed as shown in the following figure. 
    </para>
 <figure id="DDU_Main_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Main Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="figures/DDU-main.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/>
   </imageobject>
    <textobject> 
      <phrase>Device Driver Utility Main Window</phrase> 
    </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>
 <para>
The Types column shows the device category names. Various device categories are Audio, CPU, DVD, Memory, Network, Storage, USB, Video, and Other. If you are using a laptop, there will be a battery category shown up which gives information about your laptop's battery. The Device column shows the list of controllers and device names corresponding to each device category. The Driver column shows the names of the existing device drivers or the status of the existing device driver for each device. The name of the device driver is displayed if the driver exists for the respective device in the system. Otherwise, the status of the driver is displayed.
 </para>
    <para>The status of the device driver can be one of the following:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>IPS: Indicates that there is no driver in the system but the driver exists in the IPS. The Info link provides the information about the package that exists for the corresponding device in the IPS repository. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>SVR4: Indicates that there is no driver in the system but a SVR4 (System V Revision 4) package exists. The Info link provides the corresponding SVR4 package information.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>DU: Indicates that there is no driver in the system but a DU package exists. The Info link provides the relative DU package information. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>UNK: Indicates that the status of the driver is unknown and probably there is no driver for the corresponding device.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Note: When you click the Info link, the text field in the Package radio button is populated with the relative package information. Click the Install button to install the package.</para>
    <para>The Device Driver Utility window provides the following buttons:</para> 
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Refresh: Directs the system to search for devices. If the status of the device driver is Driver Missing, click the Refresh button. This searches the system for the devices and their corresponding drivers and displays the information. This action might change the previous status of the device driver. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Package: Installs driver from the IPS repository. Type the package name in the text field and click the Install button to install the relative package.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>File/URL: Installs driver from the URL or the native system. Type the file name or URL of the package in the text box. Click the Browse button to locate the package on your system and install the package. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Help: Displays the online help for Device Driver Utility. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Close: Closes the Device Driver Utility.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Submit: Submits the configurations of your system to the Oracle Solaris hardware compatibility list (HCL). </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Install: Installs the missing drivers. The Install pop-up window is displayed indicating the progress of installation.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<!--============== Working with DDU  ===========-->
<sect1 id="ddu-working">
  <title>Working with Device Driver Utility</title>
    <para>To get the hardware details of your system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Right click on any device and click Detail Information. The Hardware Detail Information pop-up window is displayed where you can find the details of your system's hardware.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<figure id="DDU_Detail_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Detail Information Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="figures/DDU-detail.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/>
   </imageobject>
    <textobject> 
      <phrase>Device Driver Utility Detail Information Window</phrase> 
    </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

    <para>To install drivers:</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to install the driver from the repository:</para>


    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click on the device name for which you want to install the driver.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Info link next to the driver status.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the Package radio button. If the Device Driver Utility has the repository and the package information in it's database, the package details will automatically populate the text field in the Package radio button.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the relevant repository and type the package details manually, if the text field is not filled up automatically.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Install.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <para>If you have downloaded a driver package to your native system, perform the following steps to install the driver:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click on the device name for which you want to install the driver.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select the File/URL radio button.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Browse. The Browse Driver Packages window is displayed as shown in the following figure:</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<figure id="DDU_Browse_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility File Browser Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="figures/DDU-browse.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/>
   </imageobject>
    <textobject> 
      <phrase>Device Driver Utility File Browse Window</phrase> 
    </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Select the package file.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Install. The Install Driver pop-up window is displayed indicating the progress of installation.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
  <figure id="DDU_Install_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Install Driver Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="figures/DDU-install.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/>
   </imageobject>
    <textobject> 
      <phrase>Device Driver Utility Install Driver Window</phrase> 
    </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>
 

    <para>To add another repository on the system</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to add a new repository to your system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click the drop-down list that is next to the Package radio button.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Select Add repository. The Repositories manager window is displayed as shown in the following figure:</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  
  <figure id="DDU_repo_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Add RepoWindow</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="figures/DDU-addrepo.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/>
   </imageobject>
    <textobject> 
      <phrase>Device Driver Utility Add RepoWindow</phrase> 
    </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para>Type the name and URL of the repository.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Click Add.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To Submit your System to HCL:</para>
    <para>Perform the following steps to submit your system to HCL.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Click the Submit button on the main window of Device Driver Utility. The Submit Information To HCL window is displayed as shown in the following figure. </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<figure id="DDU_Submit_Window">
  <title>Device Driver Utility Submission Window</title>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject> 
    <imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="figures/DDU-submit.png" format="png" srccredit="Andreas"/>
   </imageobject>
    <textobject> 
      <phrase>Device Driver Utility Submission Window</phrase> 
    </textobject> 
  </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
 </figure>

<para>Type the following system information in the corresponding text fields: </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>System type: Select the type of the system from the drop-down list. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Manufacture name: Type the name of the system maker such as Hewlett-Packard or Dell.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Model: Type the complete model number for the system being tested, such as HP xw8400 Workstation. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>BIOS/Firmware Maker: Type the information on the BIOS Setup screen that is usually displayed while booting the system.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>CPU type: Type the name of the CPU maker. For instance, Intel(R)Xeon(R)CPU5130@2.00GHz. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Information Collected: Verify whether this information reflects the details that you have specified and submit the same to Oracle.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>General Notes: Type any additional information of the system whose details are submitted. You can also type the information of how successfully you got the system and components to work with the Oracle Solaris OS.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
<para>Upon submission, you will get an acknowledgement of your submission and a link where your submission is available. The Oracle auditing team will check and publish your system information to HCL.</para>
</sect1>
</article>
